e
e e
[Music]
uh I'd like to call the uh finance
committee of October 28 2024 order and
we will start with the
resolutions tonight the first item is
temporary resolution
112-200 2027 and approve a an now
certificate um that's coming from the
Safety Committee yes uh thank you Mr
chair this is indeed coming from the
Safety Committee uh council member tener
is going to be my second on that one
this will be for three reads and uh
Chief Snider if you want to come up come
up and uh share with us uh what this
legislation is
about good evening members of council
this is actually good news this is our
Jag grant that came in from 2223 the
reason that um it's here for then and
now is um before I get too wordy the the
federal government can be a little
delayed with delivering funds and they
just got they just got delivered I
believe Trish two months ago maybe three
months ago um into our grant account and
we need to have this approved so we can
ship it out to uh Fairfield County for
their share and we keep about $7,000
from each account uh just as a bit of
context we spend that on body camera
program and we also spend that on our
intoxilizer or breathalizer
machine right thank you Chief that's
okay we'll have three readings any other
questions comments was that do we need I
apologize I thought it was one but I'm
I'm not positive oh we we can make it
one read then my my apologies Mr chair
yeah we can make that one read okay it's
okay yeah no we can make that one thank
you any opposition to one
reading so be it
next item is resolution
13-24 a resolution to approve the
issuance of a then and now certificate
for payment of invoice to American
structure point out of the LD uh lot uh
Improvement fund and that's coming from
Public Works
committee and I think we have somebody
here tonight speak to that
hello um this was the the money has been
appropriated the Po's been cut but they
actually started to work prior to the PO
being cut so we need then our resolution
so we can pay the incoming
invoices it's just PID bills yes exactly
yep I have a question yes um I know we
talked about this earlier this year but
I'm not recalling exactly what it is
they're designing are they just
designing CR
crosswalks project Memorial Pierce uh
walkways and crosswalks and it's going
to provide
crosswalks well um as as as of right now
we're under design it's not finalized
but the hope is we'll have crosswalks on
both sides of Memorial Drive I mean
sidewalks I'm sorry sidewalks on both
sides of Memorial Drive from Arlington
to Wier and then we'll have a a sidewalk
that goes from Memorial Drive down Pier
to uh Mo moves that the crosswalk that
goes over the Kroger and then we're
looking at two to three crosswalks we're
hoping one about where the Kroger
entrance is one like there around where
fir stone is and then one at Whittier
and there will be so three crosswalks
and and sidewalks okay thank
you any other
questions thank
you Mr lenberg will be my
second pardon me Mr lenberg will be
thank
you um temporary resolution
114-45 EPA Lan if I'm not mistaken
that's
correct so th this is really an early
piece uh we don't expect to enter into
this contract until um probably January
or February we won't be receiving the
loan from Ohio EPA until March um so I
was doing legislation decided to get it
off my
desk right like being proactive uh uh so
given that timeline we can do three
readings and uh Miss Tina will be my
second very good any questions yeah I've
got a few um this is Don on Lawrence was
arcadis the original designer of the
building and they're going to do CA now
um yes arcadis has we have a contract a
design contract with arcades and and
they will be doing the um construction
Administration resident project
representative and um any programming
and as builts and and all of those
cleanup things on that well what is the
uh estimated cost of the facility do you
know um the facility the current
estimate is just a tad under $10
million which is a long way from the
pole building that we originally built
that one
right do you have a feel for what their
fee was for design
alone uh not off the top of my head I'd
have to go back and look at the
legislation
okay okay that's that's all I had thank
thank you other
questions and rereadings and very good
thank
you temporary resolution
11524 a resolution to authorize the
surface safety director to advertise for
bids for the solid handling facility
replacement project also coming from
water water pollution control yeah so
this is just um authorizing the SSD to
drop bid for this project that's correct
so for our loan we're required to
advertise at the end of December and
open bids by the end
of
January yep given that timeline we can
do three readings um Mr Al will be my
second perfect any other questions
comments thank
you uh one more item is resolution
116-24 a resolution to appro rate funds
in the water Reserve fund 6027 and
authorize payment of bills for the Ohio
Water development loan for the South
Water Plant booster pump project also
coming from water water pollution
control yeah thank you Mr chairman uh we
have some invoices uh we have to pay for
this project by the end of the year and
I believe uh EPA is going to reimburse
us if I'm correct on that that's correct
this money will be coming from the Ohio
EPA loan that we're receiving on
Thursday this is really a paperwork
thing as soon as we received the loan um
owda charges us a fee and um we have to
be able to book that to make the auditor
Happy by the end of November and then um
we'll be signing the contract with
arcadas and they will have some invoices
for us but mainly I can't sign the
engineers's contract without an
appropriation so this will allow Trisha
to issue the auditor
certificate and yeah she mentioned we
have an invoice coming early November so
uh we'll be requesting suspension and
having two readings on that okay thank
you any other your and Miss ten be my
second thank you other question thank
you
Denise we're looking at
117-2013 and wellness services to city
of Lancaster employees and their
dependents and to declare an emergency
and this is coming uh from
administrative committee uh councilman
lenberg uh yes thank you Mr chairman um
councilman bischak will be my second on
this and I'd like to ask the city safety
director to address this please sure
thank you councilman lenberg I think
that most of you are aware that mayor
and I have been talking about this now
for several months um the county has
entered into a similar contract uh they
started this in 2017 where they entered
into a contract with fairfi um health
professionals basically FMC to allow
their employees to go to the Urgent Care
for free during specific hours Monday
through Friday and what's nice is it's a
set amount for the city as it is for the
county um it does not get build our
health insurance so the idea is that
hope it saves us on our health insurance
costs and health insurance premiums in
the future since 2017 the county has
been able to save $1.7
million in health insurance costs which
helps to keep their premiums down for
their employees granted they have a lot
more employees than the city has however
we would expect to see some savings over
the three to five years significant
savings so we are asking um to enter
into this contract with Fairfield health
professionals and that way we can make
this available to our employees and
their families effective January 1 uh
this the county I don't know all their
parameters but we are hoping to make it
available to all city employees
full-time and part-time status you do
not have to be on our health insurance
to utilize this benefit we are not
capped at the number of visits we're
only uh restricted in the hours that
were available to visit basically our
contract is paying for a medical
professional to see City employee and
their families um so we want to take
advantage as much as we can to allow our
employees whether they are on our
insurance part-time or full-time to be
able to utilize this
benefit any questions they don't have to
go there they can go there they don't
have to go there they can go there it's
completely free for them to go there
there's no co-pay there's no deductible
and it does not get build to our health
insurance
right um questions um I noted on
resolution 118 similar resolution that
I'd like you to speak to as well um
where that one is a not to exceed amount
buil on probably an hourly basis or a
per visit basis but this one is
not or was it meant to be on a not to
exceed basis it is a set amount if you
look it's a set amount for 2025 a a set
amount for 2026 so it's not it's it's
actual set amount it won't go lower it
won't go higher that's the actual
contracted agreement so it'll be that
set dollar amount for each year for this
contract how does that compare to 2025
how does that compare to say 2023 our
costs that's far lower than our health
care costs so we currently do not have a
contract like this this is brand new for
us um I can tell you that we spend a lot
of money in health insurance premiums
being self-insured there's really no way
for us to tell you exactly what we're
spending right now in Urgent Care visits
um I I I don't have the ability to break
that down for
you Council Mina so you say that it's
it's a capped amount did you say it is a
set contractual amount okay so let me
just so they go for anything right so
they do have a list of things that you
can be seen for and I can get that out
to you uh we've been sharing that with
some of the employees but there's a list
of of what you can be seen for it's
mostly a cute because somebody I've been
in the health since I've been 19 and you
get these hypochondriacs you get these
people they got to take their kids in
for every whip Stitch and if it's a c
them Mountain some you know people are
abusing it what happens so it's meant
for acute care so if you have a sinus
infection ear infection maybe you pulled
a muscle um it's meant for acute care
there's
no there's no capped amount right now of
how many visits you can have per year
but the idea would be if you do have
ongoing medical right concerns then they
are going to help you find a primary
care physician if you don't have one to
try and transition you over to long-term
care for someone else if you receive
shots they will give you your shots like
if you don't want to do a self-
administered shot they will give you
your shots for free but again they don't
want to continue to refill your
medications they want they're going to
to refer you to another physician for
long fre for them but not the but you
but the city's paying so there's getting
paid yep we're paying this set amount
and that set amount will not change and
well I just know of being in the healthc
care for over 40 years that there's
people that man they got to take their
kids for and they could use up whatever
and other people won't get to you know
they abuse the the privilege that's what
I'm worried about yeah um so this will
be a first time for us and the first
year if we see something like that
happens where not where all of our
employees can't be seen we may have to
maybe put a little more stringent
parameters on it but right now we're
just trying to remove barriers and allow
full access for employees um they don't
think that that will be an issue but
we'll monitor it the first year and make
adjustments as we need to okay but they
say their costs exceed 186,000 in the
first year they'll keep seeing folks
beyond that that's a not okay good good
that is correct and if it's been $1.7
million in savings for the county since
2017 sounds pretty good yes again they
have 900 employees versus our 500
employees but it's still a very
significant savings and we would hope
and expect to see savings regardless
right thank you treasure student were
you waving to say hello or no I actually
want make comment I ask more of a
question than a than a comment uh first
of all we talked about this about a
month ago uh I would suggest if you have
want to get in in depth Jeff Porter
obviously lived this in with the county
so he would be a really good resource to
talk to uh but my second question was is
city council eligible since they are
elected city employees city council will
be eligible because you do receive a
city paycheck and are considered
part-time employees of the city that was
my real question so there you go I knew
all about M again we are trying to make
it as open as possible right now if we
find that this becomes too stringent and
or that it becomes too overwhelming for
the Urgent Care staff what they've
committed to then we may have to revisit
year two or year three um but right now
again we're just trying to remove
barriers to help our employees to
healthy so good question it will include
city
council any other questions comments
suggestions and I'm sorry you're
excluding Treasurer though excluding the
that's what said I did not state that
three readings three readings thank
you now we're going to go to Temporary
resolution 118-24 a resolution to
authorize the service safety director to
enter into a contract with Renaissance
counseling and cons consultation to
provide professional mental health
counseling services to city of Lancaster
employees their dependence and to
declare an emergency and to the
treasurer and that's coming from
Administration
and you will be my second I'll be your
second and I just want to clarify the
language on the uh resolution says that
this is a not to exceed amount so is
that a fixed fee or is it a not to
exceed that we're working
towards so in the quote that they gave
us it was not to exceed uh however I
would expect that it was it will
probably be close to that because again
what we are doing is paying for
professional service it's going to be
individuals who are assigned to city
employees to see our to see our
employees yeah okay thank you other
questions
comments we got three readings Y and
finally uh we have resolution
11924 a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to accept
Northeast public energy Council 2024
energy Community Grant funds and to
declare an emergency when I say final
that's your final opportunity tonight uh
councilman lenberg uh thank you Mr
chairman um Mr bisek will be my
second and uh if you would like to
address this city safety director sure
thank you you so noek offers these
Community energy grants it is a Formula
based uh grant that we are entitled to
all we have to do is just ask for the
funds to be released
These funds expire at the end of
November which is why I've asked for two
readings uh to get our funds we just
have to submit invoices showing that we
uh spent money on energy efficient
projects so our projects that we just
started today actually are updating
energy efficient Lighting in the
chestnut building so the annex at 121
East Chestnut we are going to be
updating energy efficient Lighting on
the main the first floor of City Hall
and the third floor of City Hall and so
we would like to ask noek to disperse
These funds to reimburse us for the
money that we're spending to do this
energy efficient lighting
upgrade thank
you is two readings enough would you
like to get that moving I was under the
impression we're going to do one reading
which is fine with me but I will leave
that to your discretion we just have to
have the uh funds requested for
dispersement by the end of November so
we have another meeting on November 4th
I will leave that to your your
discretion I'll I'll second I'll second
one reading if you'd like to go that
route any other problems with Council
this will be I think replacing the
existing fluorescent lights with LED
lights which are a huge savings in
energy costs down the down the line
it'll save the city countless thousands
of dollars so that's my goal I'm
certainly hoping so we have no
objections uh from anybody do one
reading okay so be it thank you mhm uh
temporary resolution
120-24 a resolution to authorize the
mayor to enter into a pre-annexation
agreement with Metro development R
numeral 2 LLC on behalf of six owners
including Fairfield County auditor
parcel numbers 0148
98910 01400
9520 014
99540 014
99500 and
n9541 consisting of
22.8 plus or minus acres in Greenfield
Township and to declare an emergency
coming from the economic development
committee Council ho yes so this one um
and
the there's three other ones um have to
do with an
annexation um on Election House Road for
an apartment building and I think
Stephanie Hall can give some
clarification sure so Metro development
um has been working with the city to
provide U multif family housing for the
past few years um you all may be
familiar with their uh velopment on
hubard Drive um that they've started
work on and uh around the same time they
had started working on another project
right off of election house and um they
they decided to bring that into the city
limits um they managed to to find the 5%
contiguity to do an expedited type 2
annexation and when you do an expedited
type 2 annexation there are timelines
imposed by the higher advise code you
may have all heard this before I I harp
about it every single time but we have
20 days after we get served with the
petition for annexation so we usually
try to pass all of the appropriate
legislation at the first meeting
immediately thereafter to make sure that
everything is done in accordance with
the law and that we don't hold up the
board of County Commissioners in their
process and figuring out whether or not
they're going to go ahead and pass that
annexation um the mayor might have some
more information but I see Jill tangman
um with boris's here tonight she's a
representative from the developer so if
anybody has any questions um feel free
to to throw those at any one of us
questions of council
anybody I have a question um in exhibit
two the pre-annexation
agreement on the uh item five it refers
to a development concept that's
attached I I didn't see that development
concept that illustrates the apartments
that they're
proposing and it's not included I'm
guessing because we were trying it's not
a legal document that goes with the
annexation so we were probably trying to
limit the amount of documents that we
sent out um all I provide in the packet
are the legal exhibits that are
required but I'm sure we can get you a
copy of that if you would like I do I
have a copy I'm happy to show
you we're approving an annexation it'd
be nice to see what we're approving I
guess as far as the concepts you're
looking
at tonight Steve we're proving that we
can serve
that piece of property and that you know
we're starting the process but we the
final approval will come later oh well
if that's the case but the concept is
good to
know this is just a like a conceptual
site plan that shows the multi family
buildings how many units 250 not sure
off the top of my head okay I think it's
250 I'm sorry I think it's 250 that
sounds right 50 250 250 that's excellent
we need them yeah we need them thank you
okay thank
you any other questions on this um I'm
also going to reference
uh uh we have uh resolution 121
d24 uh is also part of that uh do you
want to comment on that before they're
all kind of down the line sure I can so
um as we indicated the first one is for
the pre-annexation agreement the second
one is for the resolution to authorize
the provision of services and then if
you'd like I'll go ahead and address
ordinance temporary ordinance 4024 and
temporary ordinance 4124 yeah absolutely
so um as the mayor said 12124 is to
authorize the uh services that the city
will provide so the utilities that we
are going to deliver um and and they
will use and pay us for and then uh 4024
to accept the petition for annexation
which we're required to do by law and
then ordinance 4124 is to an ordinance
to provide a buffer for an incompatible
land use so it just essentially is
saying that if for some reason the
zoning comes in and the zoning is incom
we Zone it and the zoning is
incompatible with the current zoning in
the township we will require some kind
of buffer but that's always required by
our zoning code anyway that there be a
buffer generally between those types of
uses so that that's what that is for
just in case and I understand we're
requesting suspension on all legislation
yes sir because we have 20 days like I
said to get that done you want to go
through the SEC the seconds on each of
them real quick please um for um
12024 uh I think it's Mrs
crates and then for
12124 it's Michael Wing Mr Wing correct
and then 4024 is Mrs KES and 41 24 is Mr
yep okay any other final questions on
this group one other question uh on
exhibit a for
12124 uh the pre-annexation agreement it
references
22.35 3 acres everything else is talking
about
22.8 yeah some some will be right away
that will come out of the actual
annexation removed just want to clarify
thank you
yep good any final
questions great we'll move on we have
two additional pieces of
legislation um I guess you we you've got
them in your presence you just didn't
have them ahead of time to be a walk-in
so that would be uh temporary resolution
122-2 4 a resolution to increase
receipts appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of other sources and
Appropriations with it with the county
auditor and the income tax fund
206 and that's coming from finance
committee and I'm going to request uh
Income Tax Commissioner Hamilton to let
us know what we're doing yeah um this
has kind of just been more of an annual
thing that we've tried to do at the
towards the end of the year I see what
my Carri cash is going to be
like make sure I have enough to start
off the first quarter of the next year
year and then we try to do an an
additional income tax split and that's
exactly what this is It's just allowing
us to take the extra 5 million that's
voted on to go to the sources that it's
supposed to go to and um allow them to
have it now versus
later thank you um it it's it's the good
thing is from the income lot from the
income tax increase we the voters uh
passed a couple years ago and uh until
we work through the budget this is gets
into the accounts where it belongs and
and be used appropriately going forward
any questions additional
questions and
um that will be council alss with a
second and we will have one
reading thank
you the final piece of legislation this
evening is temporary resolution 123-94 a
resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumbered
balance and amend certificate of other
sources and Appropriations with the
county auditor in the 0.15 fire Levy
fund uh 246 to 045 police and fire Levy
fund 24 2047 and the 045 police and fire
Levy fund uh
2051 that's also coming from the finance
committee and I would um call on auditor
Nettles to let us know what we're going
to do all right this um we're just kind
of using a piggyback off of the income
tax additional split we are wishing to
put the voter approved tax monies in
some appropriate accounts so if the
money needs to be used it can be used
now so this is just kind of trying to
get those monies appropriated um
following along with the cash correct
and I had one question the parks has
money in there also but they're the
Parks Board so I can't speak on behalf
of the Parks Board so that kind of
leaves at their discretion to do what
they need to do with that money at that
point in time so I can't override the
parks board right that was my
understanding I just want to verify that
that is the case and in the event they
have a project they want to get in this
year they'll coun legislation to counsil
right separately good thank you any
other questions comments from
anybody um uh councilman aers would you
be my second and we're also suspending
and having one reading on that and that
concludes the
legislation uh we'll move on to um other
discussion items and we're looking at
departmental
updates it's
you good evening again members of
council uh I just have a few updates
when when I give these I don't like to
go back months and months I try to keep
it within a week or two of things that
the men and women have done over LPD
that I'm extremely proud of um the very
first one is we're not Columbus Police
Department we don't have a a helicopter
or an air unit which is very very uh
very advantageous to have um however I
think you guys are probably give me a
lot of grief if I asked for a helicopter
so that's a problem but uh a couple
years ago off off uh Malone and then
officer now Sergeant Wells started our
drone program and they just started with
a general consumer level drone to try to
get up in the air for missing persons
etc etc and uh it was really successful
for say large scale events or when we
had a missing person or trying to find
somebody but it wasn't really you know
it's just basically a camera in the sky
um through I think it's important to let
the citizens of Lancaster know and
definitely Council to know when you're
approving our budgets through the last
couple years they were able to build on
that program and Sergeant Welsh
especially just this uh just these last
six months built our drone team so
that's going to consist of around eight
officers and what he most recently did
was able to assign um at least two or
three officers per shift to go out with
a drone so if we had a missing child or
we had a suspect that ran uh we would
have the same capability as say a
helicopter in the sky to go find them um
we attached some thermal Imaging to
these drones it's pretty amazing
technology not a huge cost believe it or
not and Sergeant Welsh is to uh
definitely be thanked for that uh
without him I don't think it would have
been as advanced program as as we have
now and I would like to hand something
out as I just share a success story like
I said I like to keep it recent just
from this morning so October 28th in the
middle of the morning um
so as you know our directed Patrol unit
they have k9's in their directed Patrol
unit um and the sh Fairfield County
Sheriff's Office asked for assistance on
a motor vehicle crash where our K9 went
out to help track uh the suspects from
that they fled but also Sergeant Welsh
and the Drone team went out and sent uh
drones up in the air and within a couple
of minutes they found the suspects and
and this car that had fled the
interesting thing or the important thing
about this um this was a ability we did
not have prior to this drone team the
suspects were only hiding feet away from
where the officers were searching
without drones they were in some heavy
brush they were not seen But if you look
on that sheet there you'll see how the
thermal imaging works and just a couple
minutes after getting these drones up
they saw right where they were and and
directed the officers to to the suspects
and found them despite being buried
under a bunch of brush and other
material so um I only say that to say
this this is very successful Sergeant
Welsh has has done a great job with this
officer Malone too should be mentioned
he's another founding member of this
drone team and now it's about eight
members strong and uh you should feel
very confident we have this ability
should something happen in the city and
then uh a couple other things real quick
just success stories recently again on
investments you guys have made our uh
directed Patrol unit just at the end of
September officer aan mitko one of our
newest K9 handlers made a traffic stop
over off of Hunter Avenue long story
short he turned that stop into a search
warrant which found over 30 grams of
methamphetamine 20 grams of fentanyl
which could kill hundreds of these rooms
here I mean a little bit of fentanyl can
go a long way um and over 22 firearms
and what happened is after that traffic
stop he wrote a warrant on the suspected
house and then wrote two more warrants
outside of our jurisdiction in other
counties uh that rounded up 22 Firearms
uh loaded firearms that are that were
raring to go so again we don't have
homicides every day around here um I
understand that we don't have shootings
every day around here although we have
our fair amount um but I think a lot of
that goes to a lot of the hard work and
dedication these these men and women are
doing just just recently too uh Sergeant
Sims let me know about uh our one of our
newer officers officer Halle made a
traffic stop brought a k9 out we didn't
have a k9 working at that particular
time but our our officers are so excited
to have this ability that he came out
while he was training he wasn't even
working he wasn't even in uniform so he
came out and training and ran the track
and we got two loaded Firearms out of
that traffic stop one or two two loaded
Firearms out of that traffic stop and
some methamphetamine so these these
individuals are killing it very proud of
them everywhere from our newer officers
to to some of our most experienced
supervisors are really doing a lot of
good things and proud of them so that's
all good thank you thank you any
question thank
you I wanted to follow up on my um
October 15th email about the lead
service lines um so
Jason lasowski worked extremely hard to
get the inventory pulled together um and
we uh have discovered no lead service
lines we have no reason to believe we
have any lead service lines so I don't
want anybody getting excited about that
um we did find just
under uh
5900 service lines that are either
galvanized requiring replacement or
unknown um you ities is continuing to do
inventories and surveys in homes as as
they're going out and reading meters um
to bring those unknown numbers
down and um so we think will be just
about 5,000 service lines that will fall
into galvaniz requiring
replacement um so the survey has been um
submitted we are now we have are in
compliance um the funny thing was the
day that I finished the lead service
line plan and signed it and we were
pulling inventory together the Biden
Harris Administration announced that
they had finalized the lead
copper uh Ru
Improvement um this is the one that we
had talked about in the spring where we
now have a 10-year period where we have
to replace all of those lines um our
sampling changes we have to start
providing filter pictures a whole lot of
requirements that that we're still
trying to figure out um the um I had one
of our Consultants send us the
pre-publication rule it's about 800
pages long so I'm still working through
that um so in the meantime as we work
through this um we are now required to
send letters to those 5900 customers
that are either unknown or galvanized
requiring replacement to tell them that
they are unknown or galvanized requiring
replacement um those letters have to go
out by the middle of November and
utilities collection has started sending
those out so if you hear from your
constituents um the other
[Music]
thing um yeah that's it we're we're
continuing to wh Whittle our numbers
down and and we are sending those
numbers out those letters out so um if
if you get calls Jason Laskowski is your
best contact he's the one that that's
tracking the stuff for the division of
water uh if someone wants us to come and
check their line um he would be the one
to contact and we will be happy to come
out and make sure that you have a good
line coming into the
house Mr chair just one quick question
uh Denise could you send us contact
information for that gentleman yes on
Council just so we can easily connect
folks with uh and it's on the letter so
yeah all right thank you
um so good news bad news um the lead
line replacement will start in 2027 and
we have 10 years to do that so so any
other
questions what what is the average cost
per line to replace so the estim we
might have 5,000 we might have a th000
so there's two parts of the line as I
explained before there's the public line
which goes from the water line to the
curb box and then there's the private
line
so we don't think that that on the
public side we have many lines to
replace um the division of water was
very aggressive when the lead copper
rules first came out in the 1990s and
got in and started replacing these
things so the question now comes from
the curve box to the house which is a
private line
and um how that comes about and the
impacts to the city
and how best to handle all of this so
Stephanie's looked at it and there's a
lot of legal issues involved in this
that that we have to work out and um
depending on how we choose to fund this
um whether we we we as the city pay for
the private line replacement or um
whether we get some kind of funding to
do that um I will say that there is
money available through Community
Development um for low and moderate
income so people are concerned about
that they should get a hold of Community
Development and that is in the letter
also so your question um we're
estimating 10 to 14,000 if we have to
replace from the street to the
meter and you're saying that that will
not be borne by the resident but
hopefully not determined we don't have a
funding source yet so so for the number
of of homes that we think we have to
replace we're talking about $70 million
if the city has to fund it um the new
water plant is $95 million so you know
we could build a new water plant for
that um so we will keep you informed as
we work through this uh USA hasn't even
worked through it they're going to be
holding a webinar in the next couple
weeks to try and explain this we keep
getting conflicting answers from Ohio
EPA so we don't know what we're
doing so we absolutely have to send a
letter out in the middle of November
telling
people basically rolling up a red flag
saying we've got an issue but we don't
even
know how we're going to resolve the
issue at this point so when people start
calling which they will which they
already have about the
inspections what are we supposed to tell
them I don't understand what's going
we're going to send a letter to our
constituents telling them they're there
might be lead and you might have to pay
for it but you might not have to pay for
it we are mandated the election to use a
form from Ohio
EPA that that says exactly what we have
to send out we're mandated to do it by
November
15th and um it's just to notify them
that they have either an unknown line or
a galvanized in need of replacement okay
I I still don't understand what we are
supposed to tell people when they call
because they will councilman nails if I
can say you can tell them that it's a
Federal Regulation that we don't have
the ability to override the federal
government unfortunately it stinks but
this is coming down from the very top
and there's nothing that Denise can do
but try and comply and that's what we're
trying you know our very best to do even
though it's rather difficult because
like she said there's a whole lot of
conflicting information it's still not
completely worked through this is your
federal government at work folks I'm
sorry but that's what it is
unfortunately and depending on who wins
the election it might just go away yeah
we don't know that was one of the things
with the timing there is a window on
federal regulations that a new
Administration can
void but they got this in before that
window so the only thing a new
Administration could do is promate a new
rule I and and the reason I don't want
to get too deep into this is I'm sure
there'll be a slew of lawsuits over this
because while we're talking about
5900 the city of Cleveland is talking
about a quarter of a
million
so
umk you we're just trying to St in
compliance I have a question thank you
go ahead thank you sorry you you were
jumping I already asked a question so
you go and I'll go after you good it's
my turn um utilities is sending out are
sending out letters are they just
sending letters to the customers or to
the actual owners of the property we are
required to send the letter to the
person that receives a bill okay and the
letter says please share this okay
so there's rentals in town so people who
own the rentals are not going to be
aware is what I'm yeah getting at okay
so as we get into this there's public
education and and then we get into the
yeah who gets notif
and but you could call
utilities and
ask and get that information if yes all
the paperworks right okay if somebody
wanted to um I did not look Jason will
be posting it on the um City website so
you could look up your property the 5900
properties the the whole inventory got
it everybody all 17,000 okay thank you
thank you Mr chair um I know you
mentioned Denise that you know there
were cdbg grants that could help out
lower income folks um at this time and
I'm assuming the answer is probably no
but are there any other mechanisms to
help offset the costs either for the
city or for the customer um is that
being explored I'm asking purely just
for educational purposes here for me so
what what the Biden
Administration said in through all of
this is we've made lots of money
available they are making it available
as a loan which means we still have to
pay it
back um and the the criteria on it says
if we take the the usepa loan
money we have to bear the whole cost we
can't do an assessment we can't CH
charge the homeowner for their share of
the
line so those are are issues that we're
still trying to figure out and my last
question Mr chairman on that on that
loan is there I I've read in the past
how you know the federal government
issues loans and then sometimes maybe
they cancel out the interest or
something like that is there any kind of
mechanism like that in place um so for
the loan or they do have Lo we don't
qualify son of a gun R righty remember
the price tag is $70 million no I I know
I'm just I'm just trying to wrap my mind
around this and get creative with
funding because yeah yeah I mean I I
share Larry's Point I want to see what
we can do to you know try and offset
this on the customers end and at the
same time I know we got to keep our
books whole too so I'm just I'm just
sitting over here thinking how to make
this all work so I I appreciate your
information though thank you very much
so the first thing and and Darren has
committed to this is is by 2027 he wants
to have all the unknowns identified and
and then we'll have a better number to
work with appreciate that thank you
thank you Denise and appreciate the
update um is there any further updates
with good news from anybody transfer
station open or was uh we had the ribbon
cutting night Friday so the transfer
station's done
Sean has received his health department
permit and he's just waiting for
somebody at the EPA to sign off he
thinks he will have that this
week very good did it come something
came in today but I'm not sure what it
was okay great thank you you have a
update I have some updates um I'm going
to be on the 114 um council meeting uh
bringing in some annual legislation
pieces which everybody enjoys so much um
the Ed Road Tiff um developer notes um
the Ed Road Flag Star Island capital
letter of credit note the annual
Courthouse note legislation that the
clerk's going to have fun reading all
that Preamble um for all three of those
I'm going to ask for two readings so
they're passed before by the end of
November because all these come due in
December um and then I'm also going to
be bringing in a piece of legislation to
um amend uh good news on the settlements
for um that we received to help
reimburse uh police and fires pensions
um they sent us more Revenue than they
anticipated in the schedule a so I got
to bring a piece of legislation to
appropriate that difference so then I
can do a a expense adjustment and get
that cash where and back to where it
needs to be so um for that one and then
at the end of um November's me final
meeting in November I'm currently going
to we're working with Denise on uh true
uping the expense budget versus Revenue
because with the water plant and paying
off we just kind of got to go through
and look at what expenses are still out
there because I don't want to pull
budget away and and a bill needs to be
paid still so um that'll come at the
tail end the last meeting in November
okay any questions of auditor Nettles
thank
you um tonight's meeting prep protim
president
skover um all I have we were going to
have an update from the building
department by Jeff Davis but he is also
sick today so we're going to skip over
that so we'll speed up my process a
little yeah very good um that's all I
got and any other items for finance to
be brought up I hear none and I'm
looking for a motion to adur so moved
second and uh regular meeting we're
going
to start at 6:55 okay thank
you hi this is Larry wz with olivedale
senior citizens of ffield County our
mission is to provide an atmosphere for
friendships and feeling of connection
with others to help achieve our mission
we rely on local support which is why
we're honored to once again be a
recipient of Buckeye Care's program this
month Buckeye Toyota and Buckeye Honda
will make a donation with every vehicle
sold thank you Buckeye for all your
ongoing
support the Frankie Smith Funeral Home
in Creator in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our our community feel free to give us a
call at
0652 stop in and see us at either of our
two locations 405 North Columbus Street
in Lancaster and 207 South Main Street
in Baltimore respect for tradition
regard for
[Music]
change
e
for
e e
[Music]
e
e e
all right I'm always late and here we
are getting started late so take your
positions um well half of you ready for
a prepared prayer and I don't have one
but I am going to give you a little bit
of my reflection from some personal
stuff this week
so just be nice to each other I Ain
everything going around whether it's on
Facebook TV you don't know what the
person next to you is going through and
we live in a I still consider this a
small town you go to church with
everyone you talk to you see them at the
restaurant they're probably serving your
food so it's it's one of those things
like they're your neighbors so calm down
it's not that big a deal and just be
nice that's my reflection for the for
the day
amen pledge
allegiance I pledge Al to the of the
United States of America and to the
repic for which it stands one nation
under God indivisible with liy and
justice for
all sorry I didn't call it to word
before that but we are now
in
session all
right call
roll Mr aers here Mr alses here Mr bisj
here M Mrs KES here Mrs hoop Mrs L Mr
lenberg Mr here miss tener here Mr Wing
here and Mr wolfinger
here all 10 members are present can I
get a motion to excuse president Porter
this evening I'll make a
motion have a motion in a second all in
favor please by signify by saying I iOS
sign let the record reflect that
President Porter is
excused uh reading and disposal of the
journal I have regular meetings minutes
dated October 14th 2024 and special
meeting minutes dated October 21st
2024 Mr President i' like to motion
to second we have a motion and second to
for to dispose of the
journal um all in favor please signify
by saying I I I I'll oppose same sign
motion carries uh reports of City
officials email dated October 14 2024
regarding green Phi Township to
Lancaster annexation submitted by law
director Hall email dated October 15
2024 LED service line replacement plan
submitted by Miss or by Denise Cruz
environmental
engineer uh email dated October 15 2024
regarding the lead service line
inventory submitted by the division of
water compliance manager Jason
Laskowski email dated October 15 2024
provided Excel version of the first
draft 2025 submitted by service safety
director Woody email dated 2020 or email
dated October 21st 2024 regarding a
special safety committee meeting for
Budget review submitted by Mr bisj emo
dated October 24th 2024 regarding real
estate settlements received from fairfi
County submitted by auditor Nettles
email dated October 25th regarding code
enforcement in zoning committee meeting
agenda submitted by Mr alers and email
dated October 25th 2024 regarding 2025
draft budget as of 1025
2024 submitted by service safety
director
Woody Mr President I'd like to um add
the reports of City officials into the
record second a motion a second to file
reports to city
officials uh any all in favor signal by
saying I I I oppose same sign
motion carries we have any
Communications email dated October 16
2024 regarding invitation to a tour of
Reflections independent and assisted
living facilities submitted by their
resident
services coordinator Deb Clark series of
emails dated October 21st 2024 regarding
a reminder notice of an exempt
conveyance from the lanaster Port
Authority submitted by Lori K of
Fairfield County email dated October
22nd 2024 regarding an open letter to
the city leadership on a boycott list um
submitted by owner of bewilderment
Brandon love email dated October 28 2024
regarding regulation Cabaret
performances in Lancaster submitted by
Robert
nley Mr President I'd like to add the
communications into the record
second we have a motion in a second to
receive and file the communications all
in favor please signify by saying I I
I'll oppose same sign motion
carries special
presentations um there is none this
evening the building department was
supposed to be here but Mr Davis is sick
okay do we have any petitions or
memorials there are
none all right now we have this time set
aside for voters or taxpayers to address
council is any anybody awake in the
audience that wants to address Council
you guys are awake I'm just giving you a
hard time all right so no so we're good
on that one and moving on to reports of
standing committees finance committee M
meeting minutes dated October 14 2024
submitted by Mr wolfinger Safety
Committee me minutes dated October 21st
2024 sub submitted by Mr bisj I can't oh
so sorry um Mr president I'd like to uh
add the reports of standing committee
into the minutes
second uh we have a motion and a second
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees all in favor signify
by saying I I
I sound like motion carried to me
reports of special committees
there we don't have any public hearings
so we are going to move on to the
reading of resolutions beginning with
the third reading a temporary resolution
10124 a resolution to authorize the sa
service safety director to advertised
for bids and enter into contracts for
mowing and trimming for the city of
cemeteries um submitted by public works
and Mrs Miss Tiner and Mr
lenberg Miss tener Mr President I'd like
to make a motion the council pass and
gross enter upon the written record
temporary resolution
10124 second move a motion in a second
any
discussion just need a grass
cut all right seeing none we'll call the
RO Mr alers yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisj yes
Mrs cres yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr
wolfinger you say yes I said
yes do i do I vote on these
okay oh canny okay okay Mr skover y yes
all right motion carries 10
to Temporary resolution
10224 a resolution to approve the city
of Lancaster Cedar Hill Neighborhood
area plan um brought in by code
enforcement and Zoning Mr aers and Mr
lenberg Mr alers thank you Mr President
i' like to make a motion that Council
pass Andross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution 102 24
second we have a motion in second to
pass temporary resolution 10224 any
discussion yeah just a quick reminder
this is just approving a plan for what
to do with property along Cedar Hill in
the future if those buildings become
vacant of any sort um there's been a
public hearing on it and citizens have
had several times to discuss it any
other questions and call roll Mr aers
yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs crates
yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr
wolfinger yes temporary resolution 10224
passes 10 to zero temporary resolution
10324 a resolution to authorize the law
director to negotiate and enter into
contract with the city of Reynoldsburg
for the produ prosecution of adult
misdemeanor traffic and criminal
offenses committed in the city of
Reynoldsburg within farfa County Ohio
and to accept payment um F this is
brought to by Finance Mr wolfinger Mr
aers Mr wolfinger thank you uh Mr
President I would like to make a motion
that Council pass Andross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
Number 103 d24 Second have a motion a
second to pass temporary resolution
10324 any
discussion have any discussion um we've
got three pieces let islation moving
forward are all related to each other
it's the annual renewal of the contracts
with the E County prosecutor
Pickerington and Reynoldsburg with the
law director of lanaster perfect any
questions and call the rooll Mr aers yes
Mr ALS Mr bisj Mrs kit Mrs hoop yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes Mrs Wing or
Miss Miss tener uh yes Mr Wing yes Mr
wolfinger yes I miss no temporary
resolution
10424 passes 10 to zero temporary
resolution wait I'm sorry that was 10324
yes temporary resolution
10424 a resolution to authorize the law
director to negotiate and enter into a
contract with the city of Pickerington
for the prosecution of adult misdemeanor
traffic and criminal offenses committed
in the city of Pickton within fafo
County Ohio and to accept payment once
again Finance Mr Wolf Mr ALS Mr
wolfinger thank you Mr President uh Mr
President I'd like to make a motion that
Council pass Andross and enter upon the
written record uh temporary resolution
d24
second a motion a second to pass
temporary resolution 10424 any
discussion no call a roll Mr alers yes
Mr ALS Mr bisj yes Mrs K yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr lenberg yes Mr schoonover yes
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes temporary resolution 10424 passes 10
to zero temporary resolution
10524 a resolution to authorize the law
director to negotiate and enter into the
contract with a fearful County Board of
Commissioners for the prosecution of
adult misdemeanor traffic and criminal
offenses committed in The Villages and
unincorporated areas within fairford
County Ohio and to accept payment once
again and brought by Finance Mr
wolfinger and aers Mr alers Mr wolfinger
Mr President I'd like to make a motion
that Council pass engross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
number
105-24 second a motion in a second to
pass temporary resolution
10524 any discussion no
further can you call the role Mr alers
yes Mr ALS Mr bisj yes Mrs cres yes Mrs
hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes M
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr
wolfinger yes temporary resolution 10524
passes 10 to zero and we have temporary
resolution
10624 star a resolution to schedules
Lancaster City Council meetings and
finance committee meetings for 2025
brought with law director or committee
and Mrs crates and Mr wolfanger Mrs
crats yes thank you Mr President I would
like to make a motion that Council pass
Andross enter upon the written record
resolution temporarily numbered 10624
star second we have a motion in a second
to pass resolution 10624 any discussion
uh yes this is just to schedule the
council meetings for
2025 anyone else and finance sorry uh
seeing none call the roll Mr aers yes Mr
Al yes Mr bisj yes Mrs CH yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger yes
temporary resolution 10624 star passes
10 to
zero now moving on to Second readings of
tempor of resolution starting with
temporary resolution
10824 a resolution to appoint a business
representative to the board of directors
for of violent Township city of L Mr
joint Economic Development District um
requested by law committee Mrs cres and
Mr bjack Mrs crates second of three
readings second of three readings on
temporary resolution 10824 temporary
resolution
11024 a resolution to make
Appropriations for planed 2025 budget
expenses and expenditures of the city of
Lancaster for physical year 2025 and to
establish line item transfer Authority
for All City departments uh finance
committee Mr wolfinger Mr
alers Mr wolfinger first of three
readings first of three readings on
temporary resolution 1102 is it second
Mr President sorry
second I'm getting ahead of myself did I
misread it no that was me second oh you
miss second I'm covering for you now I
didn't realize wor
that's okay that's why we're nice that's
why we're nice to each other just cover
and be nice all right temporary
resolution 110 second reading of
11024 temporary resolution
11124 a resolution to appropriate from
the UN incomer balance and amend the
certificate of Appropriations with the
county auditor and the general fund
10001 for County auditor real estate
settlement fees finance committee Mr
wolfinger Mr
alers Mr wolfinger Mr President I would
like to make a motion to council suspend
its rules and waves of uh third uh
second and third readings of temporary
resolution
11-24
second have a motion and second to
suspend the third reading of temporary
resolution
11124 any
discussion no uh it's just the annual
piece that we need to bring the
Appropriations in line with the county
auditor settlements any other
discussion call a rooll on the
suspension Please Mr aers yes Mr Al yes
Mr bisj yes Mrs CH yes Mrs who yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes
Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes suspension of temporary resolution
set of the third reading passes 10 to
zero Mr
wolfanger uh Mr Mr President I'd like to
make a motion that Council pass Andross
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution
11-24 second motion second to pass
discussion no further discussion we call
the roll please Mr aers yes Mr ALS yes
Mr bisj yes Mrs K yes Mrs hoop yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes
Mr yes Mr woler yes temporary resolution
11124 passes 10 to
Z I'm moving on to First readings of
resolutions starting with temporary
resolution
11224 a resolution to increase receipts
appropriated from the UN incomer balance
and amended certificate of
Appropriations with the county auditor
and the law director or sorry law
enforcement block Jag Grant police fund
2027 and approve a then and now
certificate for purchases um brought
from Safety Committee and Mr bisj and
Miss tener Mr bisj thank you Mr
President I move that Council suspend
its rules and wave the second and third
read readings for resolution temporarily
numbered
[Music]
112-pound the rules and we the second
and third readings of temporary
resolution
11224 discussion not at this time Mr
President call the role Mr aers yes Mr
ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs KES yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes and Mr wolfinger
yes suspension on temporary resolution
11224 passes 10 to zero Mr bisj uh thank
you Mr President I move that Council
pass and gross and enter upon the rent
record resolution temporarily numbered
11224 second have a motion and a second
to pass and gross enter upon the temp
enter upon the record temporary
resolution 11224 Mr bisj I have nothing
further to add from the finance
committee thank you Mr President anyone
else call the roll Mr alers yes Mr Al
yes Mr bisj yes Mrs kites yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger yes
temporary resolution 11224 passes 10 to
Zer temporary resolution
11324 a resolution to approve the
issuance of a then announced certificate
for the payment of invoices to American
structure point out of the L do
Improvement funds
3014 um this is with the public works
committee Miss Tiner and Mr lenberg Miss
Tiner Mr President I'd like to make a
motion that Council suspend its rules in
way of the second and third reading of
temporary resolution
11324 second we have a motion in a
second to suspend spend the rules and
wave the second third readings of
temporary resolution 11324 any
discussion
no seeing no discussion please call the
RO Mr aers yes Mr alss yes Mr bisj yes
Mrs KES yes Mr hoop yes Mr lenberg yes
Mr skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes
Mr wolfinger yes could you hear I'm
sorry I'm losing my voice you didn't
hear it that time thank you temporary
res resolution
11324 pass a suspension uh Miss tener oh
Mr President I would like to make a
motion the council pass and gr to enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution
second a motion in a second to pass
temporary resolution
11324 discussion uh Jeff had explained
it earlier in the
finance any other questions
please call the rooll Mr aers yes Mr ALS
yes Mr bisj yes Mrs CR yes Mrs hoop yes
Mr lenberg yes Mr scun yes Miss tener
yes Mr Wing yes and Mr wolfinger
yes temporary resolution
11324 passes 10 to Zer temporary
resolution
11424 a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to enter into an
engineering agreement for various
construction Administration services for
the solids handling replacement project
um water water pollution committee Mr
Wing and Miss Tiner Mr Wing first of
three readings please first of three
readings on temporary resolution
11424 temporary resolution
11524 a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to advertise for
the bids uh for the solids handling
facility replacement project um once
again water water pollution committee Mr
Wing and Mr alss Mr Wing first of three
readings please first of three readings
on temporary resolution
11524 temporary resolution
11624 a resolution to appropriate funds
in the water Reserve fund 6027 and
authorized payment of bills for the Ohio
Water development loan for the water
southwater plant booster pump project um
water water pollution committee Mr Wing
and Miss tener Mr Wing this will be the
first of two readings please first of
two readings on temporary resolution
11724 a resolution to author service
safety director to enter into a contract
with the Fairfield Health healthc Care
Professionals Incorporated um to provide
professional health care and wellness
services to the city of Lancaster
employees and their dependence and to
declare an emergency administrative
committee I'm Mr lenberg and Mr bisj Mr
lenberg first of three readings first of
three readings on temporary resolution
11724 uh
11824 a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to enter into a
contract with the
Rena Renaissance of counseling and
consultation to provide professional
mental health counseling services to
this to city of Lancaster employees and
their dependant and to declare an
emergency administrative committee um Mr
lenberg and Mr wolfinger Mr lenberg
first of three readings first of three
readings on temporary resolution
11824 temporary resolution
11924 a re oh a resolution to authorize
the service safety director to accept
Northeast public energy Council 2024
energized Community Grant funds in to
declare an emergency administrative
committee Mr lenberg and Mr bisj Mr
lenberg Mr President I'd like to make a
motion that Council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third readings
of temporary resolution 11
19-24
second we have a motion in a second to
suspend the rules and wave the second
and third readings of temporary
resolution
11924 discussion
none any other discussion on the
suspension call the rooll Mr aers yes Mr
ALS yes Mr bisack yes Mrs yes Mrs hoop
yes yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes suspension on temporary resolution
11924 passes 10 to zero Mr lenberg uh
thank you Mr President I'd like to make
a motion that Council pass engross and
enter upon the written record uh
temporary resolution
11924 we have a motion second and now a
second to pass temporary resolution
1924 any discussion yeah we talked about
this during the finance committee
meeting it'll uh allow the uh City to
move forward with the replacement of
outdated Lighting in City buildings here
in
town any other
discussion call the roll Mr aers yes Mr
ALS yes Mr bisack yes Mrs Kates yes Mrs
hoop Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger yes
temporary resolution 11924 passes 10 to0
12024 a resolution to authorize the
mayor to enter into a pre-annexation
agreement with the Metro development to
LLC on behalf of six owners including
Fairfield County auditor Parcels numbers
8910 014
995 511 01400 9952 0 014
9953 0 01400
9954 014
99500 and
0499 541 consisting of
22.8 Acres or plus or minus acres in
greenf Township and to declare an
emergency um this is with uh Economic
Development Mrs who oops and Mrs C could
you repeat some of those numbers I don't
think got them no all right Mrs
hoop um yes I would like to make a
motion that Council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third reading of
temporary resolution
120-24 second a motion is second to
suspend the rules wave the second and
third readings of temporary resolution
discussion yeah um during fin
committee um the law director explained
that because of the
expedited I don't know petitions um we
only have 20 days so we need to
suspend great any other
questions call the rooll Mr aers yes Mr
ALS Mr bisj yes Mrs CH yes Mrs hoop yes
Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss tener
yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes temporary resolution suspension of
the second third readings for temporary
resolution 12024 passes 10 to 0o Mrs
hoop um yes I would like to make a
motion that Council pass Andross and
enter upon the written record um
temporary resolution
120-24
second we have a motion and a second to
pass temporary resolution
12024 any discussion um this in the
following well at least the next one um
all have to do with um annexing Land by
Election House Road for the apartment
buildings anyone
else call roll Mr aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr
bisj yes Mrs K yes Mrs hoop yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes M tener yes Mr
Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes temporary resolution 12024 passes 10
to zero
12124 do you want me to read all the
numbers again yes sure six times all
right a resolution to authorize the
provision of services by the city to
real property proposed for annexation in
which includes fafo County auditor
Parcels numbers 014 8098 91 0 014
99511 014 4
9952 014
9953 0 014
99500 and
9541 consisting of
22.8 plus or minus acres in Greenfield
Township and she declare an emergency um
once again Economic Development Mrs hoop
and Mr Wing Lisa St three readings oh my
goodness this is
hoop um I would like to make a motion
that Council suspend its rules and wave
the second and third reading of
temporary resolution
[Music]
12124 second we have a motion in a
second to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third readings of temporary
resolution
12124 discussion no this is the same
reason as before okay call the roll Mr
aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs kit
yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes
and Mr wolfinger yes motion to suspend
the second third readings of temporary
resolution 121 passes 10 to zero Mrs
hoop yes I would like to make a motion
that Council pass and gross n upon the
written record temporary resolution
second motion and a second to pass
temporary resolution
12124 discussion
no anyone else no call roll Mr aers yes
Mr ALS Mr bisack yes Mrs K yes Mrs hoop
yes Mrs Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes and Mr
wolfinger yes temporary resolution
12124 passes 10 to Z
12224 resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumber balance
and amend the certificate of other
sources and Appropriations with the
county auditor in the income tax fund
2016 this is brought from finance
committee Mr wolfinger Mr alss Mr
wolfinger thank you Mr President I would
like to make a motion that Council
suspend its rules and waves the second
and third readings of temporary
resolution 122 d24 second a motion and a
second to suspend the rules waving the
second third readings to Temporary
resolution
discussion yes as we discuss in finance
committee the income tax department has
a strong collections have strong uh
collections in
2024 therefore the department is asking
to allow for an additional income tax
split of $5 million the same amount was
split in
2023 uh and that's good news for the
city a lot of money's coming in I any
questions on this piece of the
dispersement of the
funds seeing none call roll Mr aers yes
Mr ALS yes Mr bisack yes Mrs CR yes Mrs
hoop yes Mr luer yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes suspension on temporary resolution
1222 24 passes 10 to zero Mr wolfinger
Mr President I would like to make a
motion the council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 122 d24
second a motion a second to pass
temporary resolution
12224 discussion no
more anyone
else call roll Mr aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr
bjack yes Mrs K yes Mrs hoop yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes
Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes excuse me temporary resolution
12224 passes 10 to zero temporary
resolution
12324 a resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumber balance
and amend the certificate of other
sources and Appropriations with the
county auditor in the 0.15 fire Levy
fund 2046
.45 Police and Fire Levy fund 2047 and
045 police and fire Levy f fund
2051 um this is again finance committee
Mr wolfinger Mr aers Mr wolfinger Mr
President I would like to make a motion
that Council suspend its rules and waves
the second and third reading of
temporary resolution
123-142 a motion a second to suspend the
rules and wave the second third readings
of temporary resolution
discussion I'll hold
it anyone else on the motion to suspend
call roll Mr aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisj
yes Mrs K yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg
yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing
yes and Mr wolfinger
yes suspension of the rules on temporary
resolution
12324 passes 10 to zero Mr
wolfinger uh thank you Mr President uh I
would like to make a motion to council
passing gross and Inter the written
record temporary resolution 123 excuse
me -24 second a motion and second to
pass temporary resolution
12324 discussion uh yes as we just
passed temporary resolution 122
d24 uh to have the uh $5 million income
tax uh approved um this legislation uh
uh is now to to split the taxes on voted
on resolutions uh that the taxpayers did
a couple years ago uh you'll note that
the split is not available for um Parks
as that we don't have the authority to
appropriate their
funds
okay any other questions discussion Miss
Tiner yes I'd like to somebody to
clarify this I'm seeing on the temporary
resolution 221 224 for uh the fire Levy
$3
326,885
somebody want to
explain that why this is going into this
over
here problem the fire police isn't over
here as the
fire yeah the Appropriations are going
to the accounts as approved by the
voters for police and fire but uh while
we're talking about this piece of leg
isation I think it's important that I
highlight a few things that I spoke with
most of you about it but I want to make
sure everyone is clear when we were
doing payroll last
Wednesday um we discovered uh some
underfunded accounts on the fire
department for the remainder of the year
so the 246 247 and or I'm sorry 20 46 20
47 and 2051
funds were
underfunded so so we got together the
auditor um the safety director Finance
chair myself uh the fire chief um his
assistant to try to determine how that
happened so the research shows us that
on December 6th of last year um the
budget would have fully covered all our
expenses in the fire department but on
December 8th we were presented presented
a budget that did not cover the expenses
essentially what appears to have
happened and again this is recreating
something that happened a year ago and
we're not exactly clear how it
happened but instead of
having $12 million 12 M 12.6 million in
the fire budget for salaries and
benefits we had $1.2 million in the
budget that we
passed reminder I was a finance chair at
the time and I did not notice this
myself something happened between
between the 6th and the eth changed that
budget what I suspect happened is that
we were moving money from the general
fund to the fire specific funds of 206
2051 the first step happened we removed
the money from the J fund it doesn't
appear the Second Step happened and we
did not put the money back into the
other accounts and allocate from our
unencumbered
funds to uh appropriate that money for
these expens
expenses I would equated something to
like we have a savings account we have
the money over here it wasn't brought
over here and uh appropriated for the
expenses that it needed to be
appropriated for therefore I'm asking
that
tonight uh we pass this legislation to
allow this split to take place which we
already did that but to allow the money
to be uh placed in the appropriate funds
so that we can pay uh our Personnel for
the remainder of the year it is only a
coincidence that the split happened
today because that's an income tax that
happens every year income tax split that
happens every year we brought in more
money uh on the income tax side which is
the good news and now we're putting it
into the voter approved funds for
expenses so yes um to be clear we were
underfunded and police Sal or I'm sorry
fire salary and benefits on the police
side we were not underfunded but we have
an opportunity allocate that money into
those accounts uh we can cover some
overtime in the 2047 and 2051 accounts
instead of using Journal fund money so
we're taking advantage of that
opportunity but uh any questions on
that I'd be had let me offer you told me
about this thank you absolutely
counciler you have an excellent question
here so Don had brought this of the May
brought this up to me earlier today and
I got a chance to dig a little bit and
if I have to guess here's what what I
believe happened
okay at the end of
202 three thank you you were going to
have large carryovers in the the first
0.15 and then the first4 five um and it
looks to me the like the administration
like we've done every year tries to eat
up it tries to only leave the carryover
the the amount of carryover in those
funds to basically fund the first qu of
the following year because your tax
payments will catch up and so I'm
sitting here and I was quickly doing
math and you know during the afternoon
and then here Trish got me a couple more
documents so what I think happened was
is clearly what the mayor says is they
took it out of the general fund which
they should have but they forgot to put
it back into the voter approved funds
which would have eaten away the
carryover so I I I think this is nothing
more than a clerical error well I just
think this is something and this is this
is just me because I can sleep tonight
now um I just think that the public
needs to know even if something we all
make mistakes then because from what I
heard today it was a totally different
story so now that we hear this I think
the public needs to know this is
taxpayer do dollars and I don't think we
should just go okay here we're just
going to shove this over here but I
think we really need to just be
transparent let the people know
absolutely so sorry if I upset anybody
but I'll be able to sleep tonight I
don't know about y'all but I will you're
not wrong about that and I won't run any
stop signs or anything like that
but you're not wrong and clearly the you
can see what the intent was on 126 uh
and and this is a this is a claric where
where right because if anybody would
look at this one if if you're actually
looking because some people do I know
people don't think people pay attention
because the police the fire department's
there but the police department is not
right so that just kind of so
okay that gu should be clear that uh Mr
wolfinger was going to call on me to
this before your question so we had full
intentions to address this already yeah
I thought we were going to address it
actually in finance and then I thought
well I'm glad very
long yeah Mr wolfinger likes to keep a
short meeting so well I've been
chastised you're going past 7
o' all right appreciate the explanation
any other questions on that
piece
no so where are we calling the role yes
call the role Please Mr
yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs K yes Mrs
hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes temporary resolution
12324 passes 10 to zero you have any
other temporary
resolutions to come before Finance is
that hot in here or is it just me so
warm I thought it was CU I was making
fun of her reading the numbers but it's
hot okay we're going to move on to
reading of ordinances we don't have
third reading of any ordinances so the
moving on to Second reading of temporary
ordinance
3424 an ordinance to authorize the
amendment of The Joint Economic
Development District contract between
the city of Lancaster and violet
Township and to declare an emergency
requested by Economic Development
Committee Mrs hoop and Mrs Crites Mrs
hoop second of three readings second of
three readings on temporary resol
temporary ordinance
3424 temporary ordinance
3524 an ordinance to repeal Lancaster
codified ordinance part one
administrative code 12 or title 12 or
excuse me Title 5 administrative chapter
139 public transit Board of the codified
ordinance of the city of Lancaster
requested by law committee and Mrs CR
Mrs W Mr wolfinger Mrs cres second of
three readings second of three readings
on temporary ordinance
3524 temporary ordinance 3624 an
ordinance to repeal Lancaster codified
ordinance part one Administrative Code
Title Five administrative chapter 130
service Safety Board of the codified
ordinance of the city of Lancaster we
cross that by law committee Mrs kit and
Mr scoot note for
M crates second of three readings second
of three readings on temporary ordinance
3624 temporary ordinance
3724 an ordinance to accept the final
plat for ldg developments Emerald Place
project and to declare an emergency
requested by um code enforcement and
zoning committee Mr aers and Mr lenberg
Mr aers a second of three readings
second of three readings in temporary
ordinance
3724 temporary ordinance 3824 in
ordinance to repeal and replace
Lancaster codified ordinance part seven
business Regulation Code chapter 751
pedlers requested by law committee Mrs K
and Mr bisj Mrs Crites second of three
readings second of three readings on
temporary ordinance
3824 temporary ordinance 3924 an
ordinance to repeal and replace lanter
ordinance part nine streets utilities
and public services code Title One
streets and sidewalks chapter 903
sidewalks um requested by law committee
Mrs Kites and Mr
wolfinger Mrs Crites second of three
readings second of three readings on
temporary ordinance
3924 moving on to First readings uh
4024 I want to say thank you Miss law
director for not putting all those
numbers in this one in ordinance to
accept the petition for the annexation
of
22.8 plus or minus acres in the
Greenfield Township to consent to
annexation and to declare an emergency
um this is with economic development
committee Mrs hoop and Mrs cres Mrs hoop
I'd like to make a motion that Council
suspend its rules and wave the second
and third readings of temporary
ordinance
40-24 second a motion a second to
suspend the rules and we yeah suspend
the rules in way of the second and third
readings of temporary ordinance
discussion um this is the same situation
with the um the other two pieces we only
have 20 days to pass sounds good any
other
questions call the rle Mr aers yes Mr
ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs CH yes Mrs hoop
yes Mrs lenberg yes yes Mr skover yes
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes suspension on temporary ordinance
4024 passes 10 to Zer Mrs
hoop um I would like to make a motion
that Council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
ordinance
40-24
second a motion in a second to pass
temporary ordinance 4024
any
discussion I don't think so call the
rooll Mr aers yes Mr bisack yes Mr Mr
ALS Mr I quit today Mrs CRA yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes and Mr wolfinger
yes temporary ordinance 4024 passes 10
to Z temporary ordinance
4124 and ordinance pursuant to a higher
revised code
79.2
three C to provide a buffer for
incompatible land use subject to passage
of the annexation of
22.08.2012 to make a motion that Council
suspend its rules in May the 2 and 3rd
reading of temporary ordinance
41-24 second a motion in a second to
suspend the rules and wave the second
third readings of temporary ordinance
4124 any
discussion no none see none call the r
Mr aers yes Mr alss yes Mr bisj yes Mrs
CH yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
skover yes m yes Mr wi yes and Mr
wolfinger
yes suspension of the rules of temporary
ordinance 4124 passes 10 to zero Mrs
hoop um i' would like to make a motion
that Council pass and Grove amender upon
the written record temporary ordinance
41-24 second Motion in a second to pass
temporary ordinance 4124 any discussion
no seeing none has to call the roll Mr
aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs K
yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr
wolfinger yes temporary ordinance 4124
passes 10 to
zero I don't see any more legislation
that we have to discuss so praise
someone for that CU it's super hot in
here yes
I've said it twice I don't see any
tabled
legislation anyone have any unfinished
business you'd like to
discuss thank you for that any new
business thank you for that as well and
can I get the announcements of scheduled
meetings please um the next regular
sessions of council November 4th at 6:30
p.m. in council chambers November 25th
at 6:30 p.m. in council chambers
upcoming special meetings uh special
safety committee meeting October 30th at
6 p.m. City Hall 1897 conference room
upcoming committee meetings for the next
30 days Economic Development October
31st at 7:30 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference
room um law committee November 4th 7:30
a.m. City Hall 1897 conference room and
finance committee November
4th 6 p.m. council
chambers I have on my AG is there still
code enforcement meeting on is that
Friday Thursday this Thursday 28th that
was today that was today it was today
yeah was this morning yeah you missed it
my apologies is that I didn't make it
you're good like what is today I told
you be nice there's stuff going on 28th
is today
fantastic again Mrs hoop I apologize I
didn't make it
all right reading of the bills I have
zero none no bills any reason for
executive
session seeing none I would like to ask
for a motion to adjourn Mr President
like to make a motion to adjourn
second multiple seconds and we are
adjourned please remember to sign your
legislation thank
you e
[Music]
e